Guide to the Elizabeth Harriet Thomson papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elizabeth Harriet Thomson papers
1945-1990
MS 1623
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
(4 boxes)
The papers are composed of correspondence and project files which document Elizabeth Thomson's research and writing on the history of medicine. Additional material concerns her editorial and administrative work for John Fulton in the Yale University Department of the History of Medicine.
Thomson, Elizabeth Harriet, 1907-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Judge, 1992 and 1994.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1945-1990, II. Projects, 1950-1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Harriet Thomson was born on September 6, 1907, near Holland Patent, New York. After receiving her B.S. in 1911 from Simmons College, she worked as an editorial assistant at Mount Holyoke College and later at the National League of Nursing and in the Army Air Force. From 1945 until her retirement in 1972 she served as assistant in research at the Yale Medical Historical Library and then as research assistant and later research associate in the Yale University Department of the History of Medicine. Thomson helped John Fulton prepare a biography of Harvey Cushing and was his coauthor on Benjamin Silliman, 1779-1864, Pathfinder in American Science. In 1949, Thomson wrote Harvey Cushing: Surgeon, Author, Artist. She also served as editor of the Journal of the History of Medicine. Her biography of Fulton was unfinished at the time of her death on December 29, 1991.
Scope and Contents
The papers are composed of correspondence and project files which document Elizabeth Thomson's research and writing on the history of medicine. Additional material concerns her editorial and administrative work for John Fulton in the Yale University Department of the History of Medicine.
Medical historians; Medicine -- History -- Study and teaching; Women; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Keele, Kenneth D. (Kenneth David), 1909-; Light, Richard Upjohn, 1902-1994; Poynter, F. N. L. (Frederick Noël Lawrence), 1908-; Stanton, Madeline E. (Madeline Earle); Thomson, Elizabeth Harriet, 1907-; Yale Medical Library. Historical Library; Yale University. Department of the History of Medicine
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1945-1990; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence and personal papers of Elizabeth Thomson. The files are arranged alphabetically by record type.
  Correspondence comprises the bulk of the series, though the correspondence itself is scattered. The files are arranged alphabetically and include exchanges with bibliophiles, students, family, and colleagues associated with John Fulton, which show the admixture of business and intellectual life with Thomson's social affairs. The letters from Fulton, William W. Francis of the Osler Library in Montreal, and Noel Poynter of the Wellcome Historical Medical Library in London are warmly personal but also relate to their work. There is also correspondence with Madeline Stanton and members of her family. Some writers, William W. Francis, for example, addressed letters jointly to Madeline Stanton and Thomson. These letters are divided between the Thomson Papers and the Madeline Stanton Papers (MS 1482).
  The scant files of personal papers include biographical information in the form of tributes to Thomson on the occasion of her retirement and her obituary. There is also some family memorabilia.
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1950-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, Margaret, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Adams, Leslie B., 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - B, 1946-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Berg, Heather
      General
      See: Folder 45
    - Booraem, Laura Fulton, 1946, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - C, 1946-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - D, 1950-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - E, 1949-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - F, 1950-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Francis, William W., 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Fulton, John Farquhar, 1945-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Fulton, Lucia Pickering, 1945-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Fulton family, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - G, 1964-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Glenn, Frank, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - H, 1948-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - I, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - J, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - K, 1950-1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Keele, Kenneth and Mary, 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - L, 1949-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Light, Richard U., 1949, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - M, 1952-1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Muirhead, Arnold and Dorothy, 1953-1958, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - N, 1949-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Neale Watson Academic Publications, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - O, 1957-1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - O'Malley, Donald and Frances, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - P, 1950-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Poynter, Noel and Ruth, 1953, 1956-1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 33-38)
    - Q, 1953-1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - R, 1946-1974 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Reid, Richard S. and Ruth
      See: Folder 45.
    - Relf, Louise
      See: Folder 16.
    - Rose, John and Peg, 1950-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Rosencrantz, Esther, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - S, 1948-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Stanton, Madeline, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Stanton family, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Stevenson, Lloyd G., 1960-1985 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - T, 1949, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - V, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - W, 1948-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Wagstaff, Dorothy, Joe, "Patrick"
    - Weare, Florence
    - Weed, Lewis, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Y, 1972-1973, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Unidentified, 1950-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Personal papers
    - Biographical information, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Memorabilia [family], Undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Projects, 1950-1981; Series II
  Project files, which are arranged chronologically, include Thomson's writings as well as materials for her organizational work on various tributes, commemorations, and celebrations at the Yale School of Medicine and in its Historical Library. Her contributions to the second edition of John Fulton's Selected Readings in the History of Physiology and her efforts associated with Madeline Stanton's Smith College Alumnae Medal are documented. Files of her writings contain book reviews, obituaries, correspondence and publicity for Harvey Cushing: Surgeon, Author, Artist, and notes for a biography of John Fulton. Photocopies of some chapters of the incomplete biography are available at the Yale University Cushing/Whitney Medical Historical Library.
  - Harvey Cushing: Surgeon, Author, Artist, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Fulton's Rosenbach lectures, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Fulton commemorative volume of Yale Biology and Medicine, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Fulton's twenty-fifth anniversary dinner, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Christmas letter, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Fulton's sixtieth birthday party and volume: The Making of a Library, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Annual report of the Department of History of Science and Medicine, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Yale University on the Occasion of the Sesquicentennial Celebration of the School of Medicine [notes], 1960 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - History and Development...Department of History of Science and Medicine of Yale University, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Fulton issue (1962) of Journal of Medicine and Allied Sciences, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "Early Manifestations of Bibliomania in Three Collectors: Harvey Cushing, Arnold Klebs, and John Fulton", 1962? (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Selected Readings in the History of Physiology, 2nd edition, 1966
    Material related to the publication of this edition may have earlier dates.
    - Correspondence, 1958
      - A-K (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - L-Z (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Drafts, proofs, etc., 1958 (Box 3, Folder 68-70)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 72-73)
    - 1965 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - 1966-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Second edition word count, Undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - M. E. Stanton's Smith College medal, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Book reviews, obituaries, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - "Journal of William Tully," 1960-1961, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 79-80)
  - Obituaries, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - "John Farquhar Fulton" in Dictionary of American Biography, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Introduction to Cushing's The Life of Sir William Osler, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - "Madeline Earle Stanton, Disciple, the Years 1920-1941", 1981 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Fulton biography: notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 85)